A Guide to the John Steinbeck Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6239-l
John Steinbeck Collection 1934-1964
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6239-l
15 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to reserch.
Acquisition Information
Purchase 1974 May 6
Item Listing
- Letters
  - John Steinbeck to [William] A. Gilfry, 1963 Aug 13; ALS, 6 p. w/env
    [Discusses the burdensome quantity of mail, receipt of the Nobel Prize in Literature, finances, lifestyle, the difficulty of giving things away, dogs, the blacks' fight for civil rights and a childhood trip to Big Basin; briefly discusses aftermath of eye surgery, the demands of writing, upcoming travel for the State Department, Robert Frost, Charley's grave, Gilfry's poems,
    Sea of Cortez
    and his boys [ Thom Steinbeck and John Steinbeck IV]; mentions New York City, Europe, Air Forces Aid Society, a book [
    Bombs Away
    ], England, Santa Cruz County, California and [
    Elworthy W. Somerset Word-book
    ]; includes a note in another hand regarding
    Yale Review
    article on verso of envelops and "Answered August 19" on face.]
  - Mavis McIntosh to John Flemming, 1974 Mar 27; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses the break-up of John Steinbeck's marriage to Carol Henning Steinbeck as background information for a set of letters Flemming has bought from her, a trip to California, Carol's trip to Hawaii, Gwyndolyn Conger, unfounded claims of pregnancy by both Carol and Gwen, and Carol's moving to New York City; mentions George [Rippey] Stewart, [ McIntosh and Otis Literary Agency], Los Angeles and San Francisco. ]
  - Note of [ Mavis McIntosh] on an envelope stating that the following letters are from May 1941-September 1941, n. d.; AN
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941] Apr 16; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses marital problems, his telling Carol Henning Steinbeck of his involvement with [ Gwyndolyn Conger], Carol's unwillingness to give him up, claims of pregnancy by Carol and Gwen, his decision to stay with Carol, selling the ranch, buying a house in Pacific Grove, a near breakdown and his work suffering; mentions Elizabeth [R. Otis.]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941] ca. late Apr Wednesday night; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses his separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck, Carol's going to New York City, Carol's need for McIntosh's support, financial support for Carol and his breakdown; mentions [ Gwyndolyn Conger], [ Pascal Covici. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941]; TLS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck, marital incompatibilities, Carol's going to New York City, [ Gwyndolyn Conger], [Webster F.] "Toby" Street's financial recommendations, Carol's need for moral support from McIntosh, his breakdown, push for second draft typescript [of
    Sea Of Cortez
    ], Carol's watch and Gwen's losing her baby.]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941] Sunday; TL, 2 p.
    [Discusses his separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck, financial settlement being handled by [Webster F.] "Toby" Street, letters from Carol, his health, work on [
    ], a visit from Carol's father, Carol's mother's feelings towards him, [ Gwyndolyn Conger], receipt of two letters, one from [ Pascal Covici] and [ Antonia Seixas Jackson]; mentions Elizabeth [R. Otis] and Annie Laurie [Williams].]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941] Friday; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses his work [
    ] as his survival [following his separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck]; [ Antonia Seixas Jackson] beginning the typescript sale of a car and pictures for
    mentions Carol Henning Steinbeck. ]
  - [ John Steinbeck] to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941] Tuesday; AL, 1 p.
    [Discusses work with [ Antonia Sexias Jackson] on [
    ], his separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck his health, [Webster F.] "Toby" Street's handling the financial settlement and limited social contacts; mentions [ Pascal Covici], Ritch[ie Lovejoy], [Natalya Lovejoy], Ed[ward Flanders Ricketts] and Elizabeth [R. Otis]. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1942 ca. May]Wednesday; TL, 2 p.
    [Discusses separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck, [ Pascal Covici's ] handling of [
    ], the Mexican book [
    The Forgotten Village
    ], financial settlement, [ Gwyndolyn Conger], [Webster F.] "Toby" Street and Ed[ward Flanders Ricketts]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941] Saturday; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses [ Pascal Covici's ] handling of [
    ], separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck, Elizabeth [R. Otis],
    The Red Pony
    contract with [Lewis] Milestone, the [ Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer] deal, his dislike for Hollywood, her and Carol's feelings about [
    ], his health, [ Gwyndolyn Conger], The Viking Press and [ Annie Laurel Williams]; mentions Nuland's father, Stanford University Press,
    Gone with the Wind
    , [John] Ford and Donn Byrne. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941 ca late June] Sunday; TL, 2 p.
    [Discusses [
    ], separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck, his philosophy of life, the ranch, the [ Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer] deal falling through, his health, ["
    God in the Pipes
    "] and his father [ John Ernst Steinbeck]; mentions Maine, Carol's father, [ Gwyndolyn Conger], Elizabeth [R. Otis], [ Pascal Covici] and Zarathustra. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941] Thursday; TL, w/ANS 3 p.
    [Discusses financial settlement with Carol Henning Steinbeck, the contrast between life with Carol and life with [ Gwyndolyn Conger], [ Elizabeth Steinbeck Ainsworth], Ed[ward Ricketts, Jr.], [Webster F.] "Toby" Street, the ranch, the [Lewis] Milestone contract [
    ] and an [ Associated Press] rumor report; mentions Ed[ward Flanders Ricketts]. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Elizabeth [R. Otis] and Mavis [McIntosh], [1941 ca. Aug]; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses a newspaper article about his and Carol Henning Steinbeck's private life; [ Pascal Covici's ] handling of [
    ], upcoming work, separation from Carol, his health, the ranch, ["
    "],
    script with [ Lewis Milestone] and a letter from Carol's sister [ Idell Henning]; mentions Los Angeles, San Francisco, Stanford University Press and The Viking Press. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Mavis [McIntosh], [1941 Sep] Wednesday; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his relationship with [ Gwyndolyn Conger], separation from Carol Henning Steinbeck, his having been a nuisance to [ McIntosh and Otis Literary Agency], a letter from [ Idell Henning], [
    ] and work with [Lewis] Milestone on
    , ["
    "]; mentions The Viking Press and Elizabeth [R. Otis]. ]